libertyhealthshare.org 2019-06-11

# Privacy Policy | Liberty HealthShare

## Uses and Disclosures of Your Personal Health Information  

 **Your Authorization:** Except as outlined below, we will not use or disclose your personal health information for any purpose unless you have signed a form authorizing the use or disclosure. You have the right to revoke that authorization in writing unless we have taken any action in reliance on the authorization.

 **Disclosures for Treatment:** We will make disclosures of your personal health information as necessary for your treatment. For instance, a doctor or health facility involved in your care may request some of your personal health information that we hold in order to make decisions about your care.

 **Uses and Disclosures for Payment:** We will make uses and disclosures of your personal health information as necessary for payment purposes. For instance, we may use information regarding your medical procedures and treatment to process and arrange for the payment of medical bills, to determine whether services are medically appropriate or to otherwise pre-authorize or certify services as eligible to be shared under the Guidelines. We may also forward such information to another health plan that may also have an obligation to process and pay expenses on your behalf.

 **Uses and Disclosures for Health Care Operations:** We will use and disclose your personal health information as necessary for our health care operations which include peer review, business management, accreditation and licensing, utilization review and management, quality improvement and assurance, enrollment, voluntary disclosure of health conditions, compliance, auditing, and other functions related to your healthcare management. We may also disclose your personal health information to another health care facility, health care professional, or health plan for such things as quality assurance and case management, but only if that facility, professional, or plan also has or had a patient relationship with you.

 **Family and Friends Involved In Your Care:** With your approval, we may from time to time disclose your personal health information to designated family, friends, and others who are involved in your care or in payment for your care in order to facilitate that person's involvement in caring for you or paying for your care. If you are unavailable, incapacitated, or facing an emergency medical situation and we determine that a limited disclosure may be in your best interest, we may share limited personal health information with such individuals without your approval. We may also disclose limited personal health information to a public or private entity that is authorized to assist in disaster relief efforts in order for that entity to locate a family member or other persons that may be involved in some aspect of caring for you.

 **Business Associates:** Certain aspects and components of our services are performed through contracts with outside persons or organizations, such as legal services, Utilization Management Services, Preferred Provider Organizations, Pharmacy Benefit Managers, etc. At times it may be necessary for us to provide some of your personal health information to one or more of these outside persons or organizations who assist us with our health care operations. In all cases, we require these business associates to appropriately safeguard the privacy of your information.

 **Communications With You:** We may communicate with you regarding your medical expenses, share amount, or other things connected with your health. In the event you could be endangered if all or part of the information being sent to you is viewed by another person, you have the right to request and we will accommodate reasonable requests by you to receive communications regarding your personal health information from us by alternative means or at alternative locations. For instance, if you wish messages to not be left on voice mail or sent to a particular address, we will accommodate reasonable requests. You may request such confidential communication in writing and may send your request to Liberty HealthShare℠ at the address listed in the For Further Information section at the end of this notice.

 **Other Health-Related Products or Services:** We may, from time to time, use your personal health information to determine whether you might be interested in or benefit from treatment alternatives or other health-related programs, products or services which may be available to you as a member. For example, we may use your personal health information to identify whether you have a particular illness, and contact you to advise you that a disease management program to help you manage your illness better is available to you as a member. We will not use your information to communicate with you about products or services that are not health-related without your written permission.

 **Information Received Pre-enrollment:** We may request and receive from you and your health care providers personal health information prior to your enrollment in Liberty HealthShare℠. We will use this information to determine whether you are eligible to enroll. We will protect the confidentiality of that information in the same manner as all other personal health information we maintain and, if you do not enroll, we will not use or disclose the information about you we obtained for any other purpose.

 **Other Uses and Disclosures:** We are permitted to make certain other uses and disclosures of your personal health information without your authorization.

  * We may release your personal health information for any purpose required by law;
  * We may release your personal health information for public health activities, such as required reporting of disease, injury, and birth and death, and for required public health investigations;
  * We may release your personal health information as required by law if we suspect child abuse or neglect; we may also release your personal health information as required by law if we believe you to be a victim of abuse, neglect, or domestic violence;
  * We may release your personal health information if required by law to a government oversight agency conducting audits, investigations, or civil or criminal proceedings;
  * We may release your personal health information if required to do so by a court or administrative ordered subpoena or discovery request; in most cases you will have notice of such release;
  * We may release your personal health information to law enforcement officials as required by law to report wounds and injuries and crimes;
  * We may release your personal health information to coroners and/or funeral directors consistent with law;
  * We may release your personal health information if necessary to arrange an organ or tissue donation from you or a transplant for you;
  * We may release your personal health information if you are a member of the military as required by armed forces services; we may also release your personal health information if necessary for national security or intelligence activities; and
  * We may release your personal health information to workers' compensation agencies if necessary for your workers' compensation benefit determination.

## Access You Have

 **Access to Your Personal Health Information:** You may request a copy and/or inspect much of the personal health information that we retain on your behalf. All requests for access must be made in writing and signed by you or your representative. We may charge you a fee if you request a copy of the information. We will also charge for postage if you request a mailed copy and will charge for preparing a summary of the requested information if you request such summary. You may obtain an access request form by contacting Liberty HealthShare℠ at the address listed in the For Further Information section at the end of this notice.

 **Amendments to Your Personal Health Information:** You may request in writing that personal health information that we maintain about you be amended or corrected. All amendment requests, in order to be considered by us, must be in writing, signed by you or your representative, and must state the reasons for the amendment/correction request. If an amendment or correction you request is made by us, we may also notify others who work with us and have copies of the uncorrected record if we believe that such notification is necessary. You may obtain an amendment request form by contacting Liberty HealthShare℠ at the address listed in the For Further Information section at the end of this notice.

 **Accounting for Disclosures of Your Personal Health Information:** You may receive an accounting of certain disclosures made by us of your personal health information. Requests must be made in writing and signed by you or your representative. Accounting request forms are available from Liberty HealthShare℠ at the address listed in the For Further Information section at the end of this notice. The first accounting in any 12-month period is free. You will be charged a fee for each subsequent accounting you request within the same 12-month period.

 **Restrictions on Use and Disclosure of Your Personal Health Information:** You may request restrictions on some of our uses and disclosures of your personal health information for treatment, payment or health care operations by notifying us of your request for a restriction in writing. A restriction request form can be obtained from Liberty HealthShare℠ at the address listed in the For Further Information section at the end of this notice. We will attempt to accommodate reasonable requests when appropriate and we retain the right to terminate an agreed-to restriction if we believe such termination is appropriate. In the event of a termination by us, we will notify you of such termination. You also may terminate, in writing or orally, any agreed restriction by providing such termination notice to Liberty HealthShare℠ at the address listed in the For Further Information section at the end of this notice.

 **Complaints:** If you believe your privacy has been violated, you can file a complaint with Liberty HealthShare℠ at the address listed in the For Further Information section at the end of this notice. There will be no retaliation for filing a complaint.

## Internet Privacy Policy

 **Privacy Policy:** This privacy policy discloses the privacy practices for www.libertyhealthshare.org. This privacy policy applies solely to information collected by this web site. It will notify you of the following:

  1. What personally identifiable information is collected from you through the website, how it is used and with whom it may be shared.
  2. What choices are available to you regarding the use of your data.
  3. The security procedures in place to protect the misuse of your information.
  4. How you can correct any inaccuracies in the information.

 **Information Collection, Use, and Sharing**

We are the sole owners of the information collected on this site. We only have access to/collect information that you voluntarily give us via email or other direct contact from you. We will not sell or rent this information to anyone. We will use your information to respond to you, regarding the reason you contacted us. We will not share your information with any third party outside of our organization, other than as necessary to meet your need. Unless you ask us not to, we may contact you via email in the future for various reasons.

 **Your Access to and Control Over Information**

You can do the following at any time by contacting us via the email address or phone number given on our website:

  * Change/correct any data we have about you
  * Express any concern you have about our use of your data

 **Security**

We take precautions to protect your information. When you submit sensitive information via the website, your information is protected both online and offline. Wherever we collect sensitive information (such as credit card data), that information is encrypted and transmitted to us in a secure way. You can verify this by looking for a lock icon at the bottom of your web browser, or looking for "https" at the beginning of the address of the web page. While we use encryption to protect sensitive information transmitted online, we also protect your information offline. Only employees who need the information to perform a specific job (for example, member billing or member service) are granted access to personally identifiable information. The computers/servers in which we store personally identifiable information are kept in a secure environment.

 **Application**

An applicant must first complete the application form. During the application process an applicant is required to give certain information (such as name, email address, demographic information, medical information, etc.). This information is used to review your application for the sharing ministry opportunity on our site in which you have expressed interest.

 **Cookies**

We use "cookies" on this site. A cookie is a piece of data stored on a site visitor's hard drive to help us improve your access to our site and identify repeat visitors to our site. Usage of a cookie is in no way linked to any personally identifiable information on our site. These cookies are not and do not function in any way as “spyware”, do not in any way compromise the security of your computer, and do not install or remove data from your computer other than placement of the cookie itself.

 **Sharing of Information**

We share aggregated demographic information with our subcontractors, where we have partnered with a third party to provide specific services. We will share names, or other contact information that is necessary for the third party to provide these services. These parties are not allowed to use personally identifiable information except for the purpose of providing these services. Please be aware of the fact that this information sharing policy applies only to data which you provide in the course of your general use of this website, and as a Member of the sharing ministry. Personally identifiable health information is treated as confidential in strict conformity with all regulations and shared only as necessary with third party vendors providing essential services to the ministry and its members. All such third party vendors are required to protect the confidentiality of such health information according to those same regulations, and may not make use of such information for any other purpose.

 **Links**

This website may contain links to other sites. Please be aware that we are not responsible for the content or privacy practices of such other sites. We encourage our members to be aware when they leave our site and to read the privacy statements of any other site that collects personally identifiable information.

 **Surveys**

From time-to-time our site may request information via surveys. Participation in these surveys is completely voluntary and you may choose whether or not to participate and therefore disclose this information. Information requested may include contact information (such as name and mailing address), and demographic information (such as zip code and age level). Survey information will be used for purposes of monitoring or improving the use and satisfaction of this site.

 **Updates**

Our Privacy Policy may change from time to time and all updates will be posted on this page. If you feel that we are not abiding by this privacy policy, you should contact us immediately via telephone at (855) 585-4237 or via email at [info@libertyhealthshare.org](http://lhs.test/cp/pages/edit/info@libertyhealthshare.org).

## For Further Information

If you have questions or need further assistance regarding this Notice, you may contact:  

Liberty HealthShare℠  
Attn: Privacy Request  
4845 Fulton Dr. NW, Canton, Ohio 44718  
(855) 585-4237, Monday though Friday, 8:30 a.m. to 7:30 p.m. Eastern

 **Effective Date**

This Notice of Privacy Practices is effective November 9, 2017.
